Inventory of the Brown, Coalter, Tucker Papers (I) 1780-1929
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Group A: Coalter and Tucker Papers, 1780-1858., 6 boxes. (Box 1-6)
  - Children of John Coalter - Elizabeth Tucker Coalter and St. George Tucker Coalter; their spouses; children and other extended family, 1778-1852. (Box 4-5)
    - Box 4 - Correspondence of the two surviving children of John and Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, Elizabeth Tucker Coalter, and St. George Tucker Coalter with their respective spouses, John Randolph Bryan and Judith H. Tomlin, and others; genealogical material on the Tomlin and Ball families: Jud
      - To "My dear Cousin," 13 January 1830. (Box-folder 4:19)
      - St. George Tucker Coalter, New Kent County, to Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, September-November 1830., 7 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:20)
        His "chill and fever," the recurring sickness which was to bring on his early death in 1839. His wife goes to Chatham, the Coalter family home, for the birth of her first child, Walker Tomlin Coalter.
      - Mrs. Coalter, Chatham, to her husband, St. George Tucker Coalter, November 1830., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:21)
      - St. George Tucker Coalter and Mrs. Coalter, Cumberland, to John Randolph Bryan, 9 January 1831. (Box-folder 4:22)
      - St. George Tucker Coalter, Richmond, Cumberland, and Roanoke to Mrs. Coalter, June-November 1831., 5 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:23)
        In October he writes: "Uncle R. (John Randolph of Roanoke) looks dreadfully, is much worn away by disease..." Two weeks later he writes describing Randolph's estate and personality: "He is very agreeable indeed and entertains me highly with his conversation on all subjects...He is a man of the finest and nicest feelings I have ever met with..."
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, Cumberland, to St. George Tucker Coalter, October-November 1831., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:24)
        On her husband's financial difficulties.
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, Cumberland to Mrs. Elizabeth T. (Coalter) Bryan. January-October 1832., 7 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:25)
      - St. George Tucker Coalter, Cumberland, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, January-November 1832., 5 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:26)
        Writes to his sister about crops, planting, and the like.
      - John Coalter, Jr. [by St. George Tucker Coalter], Cumberland, to John Coalter Bryan, 23 April 1832., ALS. (Box-folder 4:27)
        The two cousins, grandsons of John Coalter, are infants; this letter is written by St. George Tucker Coalter.
      - St. George Tucker Coalter, Cumberland, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, January-December 1833., 7 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:28)
        In the January letter, he announces the birth of a son, Henry St. George Tucker Coalter. From White Sulphur Springs, he writes (July 27) that "the shortness of breath and the hacking cough have left me entirely."
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, Cumberland, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, February-September 1833., 7 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:29)
        Her husband is at the Springs; she would like to join him but cannot afford it. "He says he never wished for money before, as the want of it keeps him from having company..."
      - St. George Tucker Coalter, Charlottesville, White Sulphur Springs, Warm Springs, Sweet Springs, and Salt Sulphur Springs, to Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, July 1833., 6 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:30)
        An interesting group of letters describing life at several of the medicinal springs which were so popular in the 19th century. He describes his daily regimen, the meals, the baths, other tourists, the costs, and the physical characteristics of the resorts.
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, Cumberland, to St. George Tucker Coalter, July-August 1833., 9 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:31)
        Mrs. Judith H. Coalter writes to her husband about family matters while he is at the springs for his health.
      - St. George Tucker Coalter, to Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, August 1833., 10 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:32)
        A continuation of his previous letters, including a crude drawing of the buildings and grounds of Salt Sulphur Springs.
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter at Cumberland to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, March-November 1833., 8 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:33)
        In November she mentions that Beverley Tucker called on way to Williamsburg.
      - St. George Tucker Coalter, Mrs. Coalter, and Johnny and Hinny (Henry) to John Coalter, 30 April 1833. (Box-folder 4:34)
        The boys, who are just learning to write, add their notes to the letter to their grandfather.
      - St. George Tucker Coalter, Cumberland to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, 20 August 1833. (Box-folder 4:35)
      - Mrs. J. H. Coalter, Cumberland, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, January-October 1835., 6 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:36)
        Her husband is overworking, and she fears for his health.
      - Robert W. Tomlin, Chericoke, to John Coalter, 19 May 1835. (Box-folder 4:37)
        The brother of Mrs. Judith H. Coalter writes to her father-in-law asking help in gaining a position with a Richmond company.
      - St. George Tucker Coalter at Chericoke to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, October-December., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:38)
        He writes about his poor health; mentions his uncle, Beverley Tucker.
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter and St. George Tucker Coalter, Cumberland, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, January-November 1836., 7 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:39)
        John Coalter is very much concerned with gold mine projects; he now orders St. George Tucker Coalter about at his will, and has decided that the family shall move closer to him. They are dependent on John Coalter financially.
      - St. George Tucker Coalter to Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, July-September 1836., 6 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:40)
        Life at the springs, his continuing illness and his poverty.
      - St. George Tucker Coalter, Cumberland, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, July-December 1836., 6 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:41)
        His discouragement as he contemplates the move insisted upon by his father: "after seven years we have to begin the world afresh and fix and build and lay out and all that -- oh thunder - -how I dread and hate it."
      - St. George Tucker Coalter, Sweet Springs, to John Randolph Bryan, 25 August 1836. (Box-folder 4:42)
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, Cumberland, to St. George Tucker Coalter, November 1836. (Box-folder 4:43)
      - St. George Tucker Coalter to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, January-December 1837., 7 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:44)
        Regarding the move from Cumberland, New Kent County, to St. George's Park, King William County, and the difficulty of the move.
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, Chericoke, to St. George Tucker Coalter, February-November 1837., 6 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:45)
        John Coalter is very ill, and the new place is slow in getting established. Mention of the will of John Randolph of Roanoke.
      - St. George Tucker Coalter, to John R. Bryan, February-October 1837., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:46)
        The will of John Randolph of Roanoke, in which the good name of St. George Tucker is slighted. Henry and Beverley Tucker, sons of St. George Tucker are also involved.
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, March-August 1837., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 4:47)
        Home has not been settled since leaving Cumberland. Her husband has finally bought a place "about 2 hundred and 50 acres, very poor, with a new house but a very indifferent one."
      - Reuben T. Thom to "Dear Madam," 2 February 1838. (Box-folder 4:48)
        Concerning the "continued illness" of Judge (John) Coalter; offers to be of any help that he can. (John Coalter died the day this letter was written.)
    - Box 5 - Continuing correspondence between the St. George Tucker Coalter and the John Randolph Bryan families: letters exchanged by the cousins, five Coalter children, and nine Bryan children. The controversy over the will of John Randolph of Roanoke is mentioned in several of the letters. St. George Tucker Coalter was a nephew of John Randolph, John Randolph Bryan was his godson, and both were heirs, 1838-l852, 167 items. (Box-folder 5:1-74)
      The correspondence between St. George T. Coalter, his wife, his sister Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, and her husband John Randolph Bryan, form the core of the material in this box. St. George Tucker Coalter attempts to establish a new home where his late father John Coalter forced him to move (St. George Tucker Coalter was never financially independent of his father). A doctor's prescription, 28 April 1839, for the man who has been slowly dying of lung trouble and constant fever is: salts to be taken internally, salve rubbed on externally, baths at the medicinal springs and regular exercise. Four months later St. George Tucker Coalter died.
      The five surviving children of Mrs. Coalter and the nine children of Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan add to the correspondence as the years go on, for the families are very attached to one another and there is much visiting back and forth as well as letter writing. The letters of the cousins have been combined in this collection, so that an interesting picture is given of the life of this period; see a report of a traveling entertainer who visits the great houses (23 February 1847), a description of a costume ball at Warner Hall (8 February 1851) and a list of courses studied at a Girl's school (2 February 1852).
      There is much discussion of diseases which were prevalent: consumption, scarlet fever, typhoid fever, cholera, and influenza. 16-year-old John Coalter copied out a cholera cure sent by his aunt for use by two local doctors (13 July 1849).
      - St. George T. Coalter at St. George's Park to J[ohn] Randolph Bryan at Gloucester Ct. Hse., March-May 1838., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        The first letter is endorsed by John Randolph Bryan. The second was started by St. George Tucker Coalter but was completed and signed by his wife.
      - Mrs. J[udith] H. Coalter, Chatham, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, March-November 1838., 13 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
        Concerned principally with the rapidly deteriorating health of St. George T. Coalter. In June he begins a letter that he is unable to finish but by November he is again supervising the farm activity. The establishment of the new farm and the erection of additional buildings is a great strain.
      - St. George Tucker Coalter and Mrs. Coalter to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan and John Randolph Bryan, April-December 1838., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:3)
        Mrs. Coalter wrote the first two letters for her husband who was too weak to write, but by December he was again active in supervising St. George's Park, their new home.
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, St. George's Park, to St. George Tucker Coalter, May 1838., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:4)
        Coalter visits his uncle, Beverley Tucker, who has moved back to Williamsburg.
      - St. George Tucker Coalter, Chericoke, to Mrs. Coalter, 23 May 1838. (Box-folder 5:5)
        Visiting the family home of Mrs. Coalter their son, John, falls down the basement stairs and is unconscious for a time. His father writes, "the Doctor bled him and yesterday morning we gave him a dose of salts...he is now to all appearances as well as ever tho' from loss of blood, the shock, the Salts and low diet he is a little fainty when he first begins to move about in the morning." (The child survived the ministrations of the doctor!)
      - R. B. Maury, Treasurer of the Federal Union Manufacturing Co., Fredericksburg, to St. George Tucker Coalter, 16 October 1838. (Box-folder 5:6)
        A receipt for $100.00 and a demand for another $100.00 on shares of stock.
      - St. George Tucker Coalter, St. George's Park, to John Randolph Bryan, 2 January 1839. (Box-folder 5:7)
        Concerned with the business of a ferry, gold mines, and a mill, evidently part of the estate left by John Coalter to his two children.
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, St. George's Park and Chatham, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, February-May 1839., 7 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:8)
        Mr. Coalter has had a relapse, and "has lost all the flesh and muscle he had gained. Yet he makes a trip down country in April, only to return much worse.
      - St. George Tucker Coalter, St. George's Park, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, February-May 1839. (Box-folder 5:9)
        He marks his 30th birthday: "I can neither eat nor sleep nor move about with comfort and am so weak from fever...that I can hardly stand up or sit down."
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, St. George's Park, to St. George Tucker Coalter, April 1839., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:10)
        Letters written to her husband when he is on his last trip from home.
      - Edw. H. Charmichael to St. George Tucker Coalter, 28 April 1839. (Box-folder 5:11)
        A doctor's prescription: salts, used internally, salves externally, baths at the Hot Springs, and continued exercise.
      - A[nn] E[liza] Fitzhugh and St. George Tucker Coalter, St. George's Park, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, 23 May 1839. (Box-folder 5:12)
        Announces the birth of a child to Mrs. Coalter. St. George Tucker Coalter writes of the "fire in my breast that must soon burn me out."
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, St. George's Park, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, June-July 1839., 6 letters. ALS, E. (Box-folder 5:13)
        News of a young son; congratulates Mrs. Bryan on the birth of a daughter. St. George Tucker Coalter adds a note in July 4th letter: "I can't make much hand at writing this evening but I send you these few words to comfort you...my thoughts and prayers are with you may the Lord work all things together for our good." To this Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan has added the endorsement, "The last line I ever got from him."
      - "List of Negroes allotted by the Commissioners to the Children of St. Geo. T. Coalter." (St. George Tucker Coalter died at St. George's Park on, August 18, 1839.) (Box-folder 5:14)
      - Ann B. Fitzhugh, Chessanamsie, to Mrs. St. George Tucker Coalter, 11 April 1840. (Box-folder 5:15)
        After the death of her husband, Mrs. Coalter has gone to live with her sister-in-law at Eagle Point.
      - Unsigned and undated letter to Judy [Mrs. Coalter], n.d., AL. (Box-folder 5:16)
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, Presley, Hanover County, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, June-November 1842., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:17)
        Mrs. Coalter moved from St. George's Park to Presley. Her brother, Harrison Tomlin, was living with the family and takes the place of a father to the children.
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, Presley, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, March-October 1843., 5 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:18)
        Of her poverty and of the need for means to educate her children.
      - John Coalter II, Presley, to John C. Bryan, 11 August 1843. (Box-folder 5:19)
        The son of Mrs. Coalter writes to his young cousin, the son of John Randolph Bryan, at Roanoke, a plantation that had been in litigation since the death of John Randolph. The property was being administered by J. R. Bryan, one of the heirs. Young John C. Bryan, was one of the chief beneficiaries of the will, then being contested.
      - C. B. C[ocke], Belmeade, to Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, 5 April 1844. (Box-folder 5:20)
        Announcing the birth of a child.
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, Ditchley, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, 18 September 1844. (Box-folder 5:21)
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, Presley, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, January-December 1845., 5 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:22)
        Preparations are made to send Fanny (Frances Bland Coalter) to live with her grandmother and to attend school in Fredericksburg. The sale of the estate of her late husband took place in October.
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, Presley, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, May-November 1846., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:23)
        Enquires about money from the estate of John Randolph of Roanoke; her plans to send John and Henry Coalter away to school. (St. George Tucker Coalter, father of John and Henry, was a nephew of John Randolph, and it was expected that the Coalter children would inherit something from his estate.)
      - John Coalter II, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, [September] 1846., ALS. (Box-folder 5:24)
        Written from school to his aunt; "all of the boys have to get in school by sunrise and stay there until five in the evening."
      - F[rances] T[ucker] Bryan, Eagle Point, to Fanny Bland Coalter, 23 February 1847. (Box-folder 5:25)
        The Bryan place, Eagle Point in Gloucester County, is so isolated and the family growing so large that a school teacher was kept there for the other children. She mentions her brothers and sisters, and tells of a traveling entertainer: "De [Delia] and myself went to Warner Hall...and there found an Italian ventriloquist with a hat on that had little bells all around the brim...if he comes to Chatham you will probably be deceived by him..."
      - John Coalter II, Riggary (Academy), Charlottesville, to Miss F. B. Coalter, March-October 1847., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:26)
        He tells his sister: "I reckon this is the coldest and most melancholy place in the world."
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter at Presley, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, April-December 1847., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:27)
        Hopes to get a place from the sale of the estate. "Seven years this last Christmas is a long time not to have a house to call your own." Her hopes for the settlement of the Randolph estate are not fulfilled.
      - Sue to Fanny [B. Coalter], 16 February [1847]. (Box-folder 5:28)
      - Georgia T. Bryan, Eagle Point, to Miss F. B. Coalter, May-November 1847., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:29)
      - Nanie and Lucy, Lower Bremo, to Georgia B. Coalter, n.d. (Box-folder 5:30)
      - Nanie and Lucy, Lower Bremo, to Georgia B. Coalter, n.d. (Box-folder 5:31)
      - De[lia Bryan], Eagle Point, to Frances Bland Coalter, n.d. (Box-folder 5:32)
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter to Frances Bland Coalter, n.d. (Box-folder 5:33)
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, Presley, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, January-November 1848., 6 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:34)
        Congratulates Mrs. Bryan on the birth of a son, her 8th child. Mentions shopping trips to Richmond and the remodeling of the house, so, perhaps, some money may have been received from the Randolph estate.
      - Georgia S. Bryan, Eagle Point, to Frances Bland Coalter, 26 February 1848. (Box-folder 5:35)
        A 9-year old writes of attending a dance at Warner Hall and staying until 11 p.m. "We take dancing lesson of 2 hours length every Saturday."
      - B. C. Jones, Eagle Point, to "Dear Sister," 12 May 1848., 2 items. ALS. Enclosure. (Box-folder 5:36)
      - John Coalter II, Riggery, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, 29 August 1848. (Box-folder 5:37)
      - Frank Chiam, Fredericksburg, to Fanny B. Coalter, Fork Union, 11 September 1848. (Box-folder 5:38)
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, Presley, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, March-December 1849., 7 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:39)
        Consumption and Cholera are discussed as well as the final division of the estate. Mrs. Coalter still hopes to be able to buy a home of her own. Sons John and Henry left in September for the University of Virginia where they room with their cousins, Jack Coalter and J. Braxton. On Christmas Day she mentions "A dreadful affair has lately occurred at the University, one young man killed another, both intoxicated and from the south; as wicked as that is, it takes the cold blooded yankees to perpetrate the refinement of barbarism in stewing, and boiling...living people..."
      - Frances Bland Coalter, Chatham, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, May-July 1849., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:40)
      - H[enry] T. Coalter, Presley, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, 13 July 1849. (Box-folder 5:41)
        Henry T. Coalter, 16 years old, writes that he has had charge of the harvest at the farm because the overseer was sick. He has also advised the local doctors on Cholera cures: "Mama received your letter by the last post and was much obliged to you for the copy you sent her of the cure for the Cholera. Since it reached here I have copied it twice for different doctors who seemed much pleased with the proscription (sic)."
      - F. T. Bryan, Eagle Point, to Frances Bland Coalter, 14 July 1849. (Box-folder 5:42)
        A beautiful description of the Cove and the island as seen from the Eagle Point house.
      - John Coalter II, Presley, "Dear Aunt" [Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan], 6 August 1849. (Box-folder 5:43)
      - Betty (Braxton), Bremo, to Frances Bland Coalter, 14 September 1849. (Box-folder 5:44)
      - Mrs. B[etty] C. Lacy, Ellwood, to Frances Bland Coalter, 7 November 1849. (Box-folder 5:45)
        Mrs. Lacy, related through the fourth wife of her grandfather, John Coalter, was like an older sister to Frances Bland Coalter, and the affectionate relationship between the two continued for many years.
      - Mrs. B. C. Lacy, Chatham, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, 23 November 1849. (Box-folder 5:46)
        The Lacy's are preparing to move into Ellwood, the former summer home of John Coalter.
      - John Coalter II, University of Virginia, to Frances Bland Coalter, 24 November 1849. (Box-folder 5:47)
      - Frances Bland Coalter, Chatham, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, 1 January 1850. (Box-folder 5:48)
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, Presley, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, January-July 1850., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:49)
        Letters written before and after a long visit. There were ties between the families despite the distance between them. Mrs. Coalter fears her youngest son, Saint [George], has Typhoid fever.
      - Lucy Lindley, Ingleside, to Frances Bland Coalter, February-November 1850., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:50)
        A school friend tells of a visit to Richmond to see the relics of Gen. and Mrs. Washington.
      - Mrs. B. C. Lacy, Ellwood, to Frances Bland Coalter, 2 April 1850., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:51)
      - Georgia B[ryan], Eagle Point, to Frances Bland Coalter, 13 April 1850. (Box-folder 5:52)
      - Georgia Bryan, Eagle Point, to Frances Bland Coalter, February-August 1851., 3 letters. ALS. Cover lacking. (Box-folder 5:53)
        About life in the great houses of Virginia, excursions on river boats, dances, and the like. Mentions a fancy ball where everyone appeared in a mask and gown, "You cannot tell a man from a woman. They go about in this costume for some time and have a dance...one gentleman went draped as a lady and no one found him out,...one went as a monk in robes and with his beads..."
      - Mrs. B. C. Lacy, Greenwood and Ellwood, to Frances Bland Coalter, March, August 1851., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:54)
        "When will your new house, or rather, new home be ready for you? (Frances Bland Coalter's mother has finally been able to buy a house, Stanley.)
      - Lucy Lindley, Ingleside, to Frances Bland Coalter, April, July 1851., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:55)
      - B.C. Lacy, Ellwood, to "My dear Cousin" [Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan], 8 May 1851. (Box-folder 5:56)
      - Mrs. Judith H. Coalter, Presley, to Mrs. Elizabeth T. Bryan, June-December 1851., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 5:57)
        Mentions the war threat: "my anxiety about a lasting peace and the welfare of my children preys very much on my spirits."
      - Elizabeth Gordon, Eliwood, to Frances Bland Coalter, 1 September 1851. (Box-folder 5:58)
        Announces the birth of a daughter to Mrs. Lacy.
      - Mannie [Tomlin], Lower Bremo, to Fanny [Coalter], 22 September 1851. (Box-folder 5:59)